<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A map of judgement, or, A pattern for judges delivered in a sermon at the Assizes holden at Guildford-in-Surrey, July 23d, 1666 before Sr. Orlando Bridgeman, Kt., Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas, and Sr. Samuel Brown, Kt. / by W. Hampton ...</title>
            <author>Hampton, William, 1599 or 1600-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12738678</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12738678</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45484)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 693:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A map of judgement, or, A pattern for judges delivered in a sermon at the Assizes holden at Guildford-in-Surrey, July 23d, 1666 before Sr. Orlando Bridgeman, Kt., Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas, and Sr. Samuel Brown, Kt. / by W. Hampton ...</title>
                  <author>Hampton, William, 1599 or 1600-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.I. for H. Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XVIII, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Judges --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Map of Judgement, Or a Pattern for JUDGES. Delivered in a Sermon. at the Aſſizes holden at <hi>Guildford</hi> in <hi>Surrey; July.</hi> 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1666. BEFORE S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Orlando Bridgeman; K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas, AND S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Samuel Brown, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Hampton;</hi> Rector of <hi>Blechingley.</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. Chron. 19. 6; 7.</bibl> And he ſaid to the Judges; take heed what ye do; for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord; who is with you in the Judgement: Wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed, and do it; for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>H. Brome</hi> over againſt the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93067:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93067:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93067:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The Honourable Sr. <hi>Orlando Bridgeman;</hi> Kt. Lord Chief Juſtice of his Majeſties Court of Common Pleas, and Sr. <hi>Samuel Brown;</hi> Kt. another of his Majeſties Juſtices of the ſaid Court. Grace, Mercy, and Peace, with all happineſs in this World, and everlaſting bleſſedneſs in that which is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Honourable Sirs;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon being Preached in your hearing, and received with the good liking of that numerous audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then preſent (as I underſtand) and as appeared by their more than uſual attention while it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering; for what was ſaid of our dear Saviour, I may without oſtentation ſay of my poor ſelf, <hi>The eyes of all that were in the Synagogue were faſtned on him. Luke 4.20.</hi> And being importuned by ſome worthy friends to make it more publick, I have condiſcended, hoping it may adde ſome few mites to the publick trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, for the Churches good. And I aſſented chiefly upon theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe it was ſo well approved and accepted by ſuch pious, learned, and judicious Worthies, as your Honours, great aſſertors of piety, equity, and right, by whom, this Circuit hath for ſome years, been honoured, as well as bleſſed, in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93067:3"/>
            <p> Secondly, Becauſe I have ſome hopes, it may put, at leaſt a ſtop to that great inundation of Sin and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, which is gone forth into the Land, by ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating his Majeſties Commiſſioners in all places, to a diligent diſcharge of their duties in ſo good a work.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it may ſtand as a laſting evidence of my humble and cordial thankfulneſſe to that ſupreme Moderator of all things, for enabling me, a poor worm, to labour ſo long in his Vineyard, and to bring forth ſome fruits both in Youth and Age, and to perform ſuch a task twice, at ſuch a diſtance of time, the interval of more than ten Olympiads intervening. I cannot think of meeter perſons to Devote it to, than your Honours, who ſo well approved both the manner of delivery, and the matter delivered; which I humbly beſeech you to accept in good part, and to ſhelter it under your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. It is Printed, almoſt verbatim, as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, only in the laſt point ſome little enlargement is made, which I was forced then to omit, leaſt prolixity ſhould have impeded your moſt weighty buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Thus humbly craving pardon for my boldneſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending this poor Work to the bleſſing of God, for the glory of his Name, and good of his People, I commit you to his ſafe Protection, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble Servant in the work of the Lord, <hi>William Hampton.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in</hi> Blechingley. <date>Aug <hi>13. 1666.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93067:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Map of Judgement, or, a Pattern for JUDGES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GENESIS. 18.25.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.52. <hi>Every Scribe which is inſtructed for the Kingdome of Heaven, is like unto a man that is an Houſholder, which bringeth forth out of his treaſure, things new and old.</hi> The ſame with Gods help, I hope to do now. It was full forty years ago, the ſeventh of this month, (the Lords holy Name be praiſed) that I ſpake ſomething upon this Text, on the like occaſion, and in this County, at the Aſſizes holden at <hi>Riegate, July</hi> 7. 1626, and if I ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to harpe upon ſome of the old notes, I dare ſay, moſt, if not all here preſent, would keep my counſel; It will be new to them; and yet I doubt not, but to bring forth ſome things new, as well as old. It is true, we are to live <hi>Praeceptis non Exemplis,</hi> by Precepts not by Examples; and yet experience proves, <hi>Exemplis magis quam praeceptis,</hi> we are apt to be led rather by pattern than by precept, and in framing the courſe of our lives, Example for the moſt part more prevails than Exhortation. Wherefore, this being a time allotted for Judgment, I have made choice to ſet before you a Map of Judgment, the Pattern and Example of a great Judge, the Judge of Judges, the Judge of all the world; in his place you ſit, he lends a part of his honour to you, and inveſts you with his power, he vouchſafes his name unto you, <hi>dixi dii eſtis;</hi> whom then ſhould the Servant imitate but his Lord, the Subject but his Soveraign, the Little Gods of the earth, but the great God of Heaven and Earth? the Judges of a Land, or little world, but the Judge of all the world? <hi>Zeno</hi> being asked by his friends how they might keep themſelves to right, when he was gone, anſwered, <hi>ſi me preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſemper putetis;</hi> if you imagine me to be alwaies preſent with you, the beholder of your actions. And ſurely a ſtronger motive you cannot have to keep your ſelves to equity and right, <hi>quam Deum preſentem ſemper cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93067:4"/>than to have this great Judge alwaies before your eyes, the pattern and ſpectatour of all your proceedings: hee ſees our works, he hear our words, he knows our thoughts; if we do ill, will not he puniſh us? if we do well, will not he reward us? if we do right, will not he applaud it? if we do wrong, will not he revenge it? Yes verily: <hi>For ſhall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words were uttered by <hi>Abraham</hi> upon this occaſion, when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was minded to deſtroy the City of <hi>Sodom,</hi> whoſe ſins cryed to his Throne for vengeance; he firſt after the manner of men, pawſed on the matter, and was loath to do it, till he had taken advice of a friend, and made <hi>Abraham</hi> (whom St. <hi>James</hi> calleth the friend of God) privie to his purpoſe; <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham the thing which I do? Abraham</hi> being hereby aſſured of Gods love and favour, began to argue the matter, and became an humble ſuitor for his ſinful neighbours, and knowing them to be <hi>in miſericordia provero clamore,</hi> puts up his petition into the Chancery of Gods boundleſs mercy, that if there could be fifty good men found within the City, he would be pleaſed to ſpare the whole for their ſake. The Lord grants his petition; <hi>Abraham</hi> goeth ſtraight way with a privy ſearch through the City of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and after his labour loſt, he makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto God, with a <hi>non est inventus;</hi> yet he proceeds on in his ſuit, and craving pardon for his boldneſs, he obtains a Writ <hi>Admelius inquirendum,</hi> and then falls from fifty to forty five, from forty five to forty, from forty to thirty, from thirty to twenty, from twenty to ten, which ſmall number had that populous City afforded, he would have ſpared all for their ſakes; <hi>I will not deſtroy it for tens ſake.</hi> And he brings theſe words as a convincing Argument, that it ſtood not with the reputation of the Almighty, who is the great Lord chief Juſtice of the world, to do injuſtice, to burn innocents, with nocents, to flay the righteous with the wicked. <hi>Wilt thou alſo deſtroy the righteous with the wicked? Peradventure there ſhall be fifty righteous within the City, wilt thou deſtroy and not ſpare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein? That be far from thee, to do after this manner, to ſlay the righteous with the wicked, and that the Righteous ſhould be as the wicked, that be far from thee: ſhall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi> Not that <hi>Abraham</hi> in this expoſtulation doth make any doubt of the Juſtice of God; for this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation is indeed a vehement aſſeveration; ſo that in this negative que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is emphatically implyed an affirmative poſition, as if he had ſaid, <hi>I know the Judge of all the world will do right.</hi> Frequent in holy Writ, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations in the negative, to affirm the more earneſtly. So <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzi, Went not my heart with thee,</hi> &amp;c. Yes, I know all thy tampering and juggling well enough. So here, <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the world do right?</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93067:4"/>is all one, as if he had ſaid, <hi>I am ſure the Judge of all the Earth will do right.</hi> The words being thus reſolved, you may note in them three parts. A Judge, his Circuit, and his Judgement. The Judge is the Lord; his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit very large, All the Earth; His Judgement moſt juſt and right, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if you will, as the Text hath four words, ſo I will put four quaeries to be briefly diſcuſſed: <hi>Quis? Quos? Quando? Quomodo:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>Quis,</hi> Who this Judge is? and that is Chriſt the Lord of the World; he it was that here talked with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that appeared to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, and Fathers in the Old Teſtament.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>Quos,</hi> Whom he ſhall judge; All the Earth, or the whole World.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, <hi>Quando,</hi> When he ſhall Judge; The time is to come at the end of the World, noted in the Particle, <hi>ſhall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, <hi>Quomodo,</hi> How he ſhall judge; Not according to the corrupt Faſhion of the world; <hi>Sed ſecundum norman Juſtitiae,</hi> according to the Rule of Juſtice, according to equity and right: <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the world do right?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I begin with him, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beginning and the end of all our actions, yea of all things, and that is, <hi>Quis,</hi> who this Judge is? namely Chriſt the Son of God, God and man, the Meſſiah, the Saviour and Redeemer of the world; he is made Lord Chief-Juſtice of all the world; and he hath it by Commiſſion: hear his own Teſtimony for it, and we know that his Teſtimony is true, <hi>John</hi> 5.22. <hi>The Father Judgeth no man, but hath committed all Judgement unto the Son, becauſe that all men ſhould honour the Son even as they honour the Father.</hi> Upon which place St. <hi>Auſtin Tractat.</hi> 19. in <hi>Johan.</hi> moves a doubt, whether the Father ſhall be excluded in the laſt Judgement, which he reſolves by comparing theſe words, with the 27th <hi>verſe, He hath given him power to execute Judgement, becauſe he is the Son of Man.</hi> The Father (ſaith he) ſhall not be ſeen coming to Judgment, but yet he ſhall not be excluded from giving of Judgement, he hath the ſame power with the Son, for the power of all the three perſons is coaequal. The Son only ſhall be ſeen in Judgement; The Judge ſhall appear in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſhape, <hi>forma humana,</hi> in a humane form; <hi>They ſhall ſee him onely whom they have pierced;</hi> He ſhall come to judgement, and ſit on the Throne of judgement, and pronounce judgement in the very ſame body wherein hee ſuffered and dyed; That Forme ſhall be Judge, which ſtood before a Judge; and he ſhall judge that was judged; and hoe ſhall judge juſtly, that was judged unjuſtly; <hi>For the Father hath given him power to Execute Judgement, becauſe he is the Son of man;</hi> that is, becauſe he did ſo far condeſcend and debaſe himſelf, as to come into the world, and aſſume our Nature to his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93067:5"/>God-head, to be greatly humbled, to do and ſuffer ſo much for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, therefore the Father will ſo highly exalt him, that in the ſame nature, in the ſame forme, in the ſame body he ſhall ſit to judge the world: <hi>He hath appointed a day, in the which he will judge the world in Righteouſneſs, by that man whom he hath ordained,</hi> Acts 17.31.</p>
            <p>But doth not the Apoſtle ſay, that <hi>the Saints ſhall judge the world?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2. and Chriſt to his Apoſtles, <hi>Ye which have followed me in the Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Son of man ſhall ſit upon the Throne of his Glory, ye alſo ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael,</hi> Matth. 19.28.</p>
            <p>Theſe places are to be underſtood, either of judging the world. 1. By their Doctrine, or, 2. By their good examples and holy lives, as Chriſt ſaid, that the Queen of the South, and the <hi>Ninevites</hi> ſhould riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the men of that generation, and Condemn them: or, 3. Of the atteſtation and approbation which they ſhall give to the righteous judgement of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1, 2. They ſhall ſit Aſſiſtants with him, and be by his ſide, (like privie Counſellors to the King.) As we ſee here at an Aſſize, there be many inferiour Juſtices, who ſit on the Bench, and are Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants to the Judge, not that they give ſentence in any matter; for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Judge, but they ſit as approvers and teſtifiers of the juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; So ſhall it be with the Saints; they ſhall ſit as Aſſiſtants with Chriſt, to approve and applaud the righteous dealing of that great Judge, but to him alone belongs the pronouncing of Sentence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. O what a ſtrong conſolation may this be to all the Faithful people of Chriſt, in that he who ſaved them, ſhall judge them! he who is fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bone; he who gave his fleſh, and body, and blood, and life, and all to redeem them? No comfort like this to a guilty perſon arraigned at the Barre, as to have the Judge to be his friend; to ſpeak for him, to plead for him, to defend, to protect him: But ſo it ſhall be with the faithful at that day; they ſhall have their friend to bee their Judge; their Head, their Husband, their Kinſman, their Brother; their Redeemer, their Interceſſor, their Saviour: Surely it muſt needs go well with them; their cauſe ſhall be heard before him, who loved them ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he dyed for them; The great Judge of all the world ſhall acquit them, who then ſhall lay any thing to their charge? <hi>It is God that Juſtifieth</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>who then ſhall Condemn? It is Chriſt that Judgeth, there is therefore no Condemnation to them that are his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And this alſo ſhall ſtrike confuſion to his enemies; <hi>They ſhall ſee him coming in the Clouds of Heaven, and ſitting on the Throne of Glory, whom they pierced;</hi> Whom they pierced with their bands, with their ſins, with their tongues, with their oaths, with their blaſphemies, and impieties, he whom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93067:5"/>they deſpiſed, whoſe call they neglected, whoſe Goſpel they rejected, whoſe Word they contemned, whoſe Mercy they abuſed, whoſe Miniſters they ſlighted, whoſe Ambaſſadours they wronged; he ſhall be their Judge: For he is of ſuch omnipotency, that he ſhall force his enemies, and all to appear before his Tribunal. And thus having briefly diſcuſſed the firſt quaerie, <hi>Quis,</hi> who this Judge ſhall be; I paſs to the ſecond, <hi>Quos,</hi> whom hee ſhall Judge? All the Earth. A very large Circuit; other Judges are Judges of but ſome ſmall Circuit or corner of the Earth; Judges of earth, and Judges, who (when their breath goeth forth) muſt fall to the earth, and turn to a little lump of earth as well as others; but this is the Judge of all the Earth; <hi>Judex totius mundi,</hi> the Judge of all the world: All the world, yea, all the men of the world muſt appear before his Tribunal, <hi>We muſt all appear before the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>Before him ſhall be gathered all Nations,</hi> Mat. 25.32. All Nations and Countries, all People and Languages, all men, of what eſtate or condition ſoever: The King that Ruleth, the Judge that Judgeth, the Lawyer that pleadeth, the Client that ſueth, the witneſs that ſweareth, the Jury that, cenſureth, the Paſtour that ſpeaketh, the people that heareth, high and low, rich and poor, young and old, we muſt all appear before this mighty Judge; He is <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex vivorum &amp; mortuorum,</hi> Judge of the living and the dead; Thoſe who are found alive at his coming, ſhall in a moment be changed, thoſe that dyed before, ſhall in a moment be raiſed, all ſhall appear; <hi>All that are in the graves, ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they ſhall conse forth, they that have done good to the Reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil to the Reſurrection of condemnation,</hi> John 5.28, 29. All that are in the Graves, yea, and more than all that are in the Graves; all that have dyed ſince the beginning of the world; though they have been drowned in the Sea; and devoured by fiſhes; though they have been burned in the fire, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to Aſhes; though their fleſh hath been made a banquet to the beaſts of the field, and fowls of the Air; yet at the Trumpet of the Arch-Angel, at the voice of the Son of God, they ſhal all revive; the Trump ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall riſe, and come to judgement; There ſhall not miſs one man, woman, or childe from the beginning of the Creation; All ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, every one <hi>propria perſona,</hi> in his own proper perſon; no Proxie, no Atrourney ſhall ſerve the turne at that day. Thus much St. <hi>John</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. Where was revealed to him, the Majeſty of this mighty Judge, and the manner of this grand Aſſize. <hi>I ſaw a great white Throne, and one who ſate upon it, from whoſe Face fled away, both the earth, and the Heaven; and I ſaw the dead both great and ſmall ſtand before God; for the Sea gave up her dead, which were in her, and death and Hell delivered up the dead that were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93067:6"/>in them, and they were judged every man according to their works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, ſhall all be judged, as well the Godly, as the Godleſs, as well the faithful as the faithleſs? have we not the Judges own Word and Warrant for the contrary, confirmed with a double Seal, that the faithful who hear and obey his Word, and believe in him, ſhall not bee judged; <hi>Amen, amen dico vobis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, hee that heareth my word, and believeth in him that ſent me, hath everlaſting Life, and ſhall not come into Judgement, but paſſeth from death unto life,</hi> Joh. 5.24.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which properly ſignifieth judgement, is ſometimes taken for, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to Judge, for to condemn, often in the Scripture: So that when Chriſt ſaith, the faithful ſhall not come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into judgement, the meaning is, into condemnation, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> well noteth on the place; There is (ſaith he) <hi>Judicium abſolutionis, &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium condemnationis,</hi> the Judgement of abſolution, and the Judgement of condemnation: Or as <hi>Aquinas</hi> aptly diſtinguiſheth, in the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are two things, <hi>diſcuſſio peccatorum, &amp; retributio praemiorum,</hi> a diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, and a retribution of rewards. All ſhall appear, both the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and the faithleſs, though to a different judgement: The faithful to the judgement of abſolution, <hi>ad retributionem praemioruns,</hi> to partake of the reward; the wicked to the judgement of condemnation, <hi>ad diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem peccatorum,</hi> to anſwer for their ſins: Their ſins ſhall be diſcuſſed, ſearched and ſifted moſt narrowly; their moſt ſecret ſins ſhall be laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the view of the whole world, before that great aſſembly both of Men and Angels; and not onely laid open, but laid to their charge; the Book of Conſcience ſhall be opened, and accuſe them more than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes: and according to their ſins, ſhall a fearful doom be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, an everlaſting ſeparation from that moſt beatifical Viſion of the Deity, to a terrible Habitation, and aſſociation with wicked Devils; <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 25. But as for the Godly and Faithful, who are reconciled to their Heavenly Father, by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his bleſſed Son, though they appear alſo at this great Aſſize, yet it ſhall be to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of abſolution, to be acquitted, pardoned, ſaved, There ſhal no <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſio peccatorum</hi> paſs upon them; their ſins ſhall not be laid open, nor laid to their charge, nor hamed, nor mentioned, nor brought forth at that day, ſo much as to accuſe them, or grieve, or ſhame them, much leſs to condemn them; but they ſhall all be waſhed away in the blood of the Lamb, blotted out, forgotten and forgiven, as if they had never been; <hi>For I will forgive their iniquities, and I will remember their ſin no more,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93067:6"/>Jer. 31.34. and again, <hi>Jer</hi> 50.20. <hi>In thoſe dates, and at that time, ſaith the Lord, the iniquity of Iſrael ſhall be ſought for, and there ſhall be none, and the ſins of Judah, and they ſhall not be found; for I will pardon them whom I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi> So ſhall the Propheſie of <hi>Balaam</hi> be fulfilled; <hi>He ſhall ſee none Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in Jacob, nor tranſgreſſion in Iſrael,</hi> Numb. 23.21.</p>
            <p>Their ſins indeed ſhall be ſought for; Satan that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious enemie of humane happineſs, ſhall labour to accuſe them, to bring forth their ſins againſt them, and lay them to their Charge; but the true <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the lover of men will not ſuffer him, he will throw them all into the bottom of the Sea, caſt them behinde his back, nail them to the Croſs, bury them in the grave of his Son, drown them in his blood, and remove them further than the Eaſt is from the Weſt; that they ſhall not be found, nor remembred, nor brought forth againſt his faithful people at that day: So that though they appear, it ſhall not be <hi>ad diſcuſſionem peccatorum,</hi> to have their ſins diſcuſſed, ſifted, examined, cenſured like the wicked; but <hi>ad retributionem praemiorum,</hi> to have their labours and good works re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded; yea, to have the works of Chriſt, which are now appropriate to them, and made theirs by imputation, Crowned with a Diadem of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Immortality in the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall demand with the Diſciples, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but tell us, when ſhall theſe things be? I anſwer, Here ye poſe me indeed: Theſe things ſhall ſo come to paſs, I am ſure, but when, or how ſoon, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell; It is the next quaerie to be diſcuſſed, <hi>Quando,</hi> When he ſhall Judge, noted in the future ſign <hi>ſhall:</hi> the time is to come, at the end of the World.</p>
            <p>That there ſhall be ſuch a day is moſt certain, moſt uncertain when it ſhall be: we have the Word of God to confirm the certainty of it; <hi>Our God ſhall come, and ſhall not keep ſilence; there ſhall go before him a conſuming fire,</hi> Pſal. 50.3. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall ſhow himſelf from Heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, to render vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. We have his promiſe for it, <hi>Behold I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give to every man according as his work ſhall be,</hi> Rev. 22.12. We have his Oath for it; <hi>The Mighty Angel lift up his hand to Heaven, and ſware by him that liveth for ever and, ever who Created Heaven, and the things that are therein, and the Earth, and the things that are therein, and the Sea, and the things which are therin, that time ſhould be no more,</hi> Rev. 10.6. We have the Juſtice of God to confirm it; it ſtands with his Juſtice, that there ſhould be ſuch a day; God is moſt juſt, he wil ſhew mercy to the Godly, and judgement to the wicked; he will (as Sr. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) reward every man according to his works: but he doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb facs="tcp:93067:7"/>ſo in this life; for the wicked enjoy as many outward bleſſings as the Godly, All things come alike to all, and the ſame condition is to the Juſt, and to the unjuſt, to him that Sacrifizeth, and to him that Sacrifizeth not: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith the Preacher. Yea, the wicked in this world, for the moſt part, enjoy more felicity, than Gods Children; they laugh, when theſe weep; they ſing when theſe ſigh; they proſper, when theſe are perſecuted; they flouriſh, when theſe are afflicted; they are in pompe and jollity, when theſe are in want and miſery: <hi>ſic fuit a principio,</hi> from the beginning it hath been ſo; <hi>Abel,</hi> righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> lies dead at the feet of his wretched Brother <hi>Cain:</hi> Chaſte <hi>Joſeph</hi> is fettered in the Dungeon, while his lewd Lady flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth in her braverie: the <hi>Hebrews</hi> groan under their heavy burthens, ſweat in the Brick-Kills, while the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> live at eaſe, domineering over them: <hi>Elias</hi> fainteth in the Deſart, while <hi>Jezabel</hi> painteth in her Cloſet: <hi>Daniel</hi> quaketh in the den of Lyons, but the proud King <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> quaffeth among his boon Companions: The holy Prophets of God are mocked, ſcourged, ſawn aſunder, ſlain with the Sword, while their cruel Perſecutors ſwell, and ſway, and triumph, in their ſorrows: <hi>John</hi>'s head lies bleeding in the Platter, while <hi>Herod</hi> is ſmiling at his Revels, and Dancing among his Damſels: <hi>Lazarus</hi> Famiſheth, while <hi>Dives</hi> Feaſteth. Therefore, there muſt needs be a general day of Judgement; when God will give to every man his right; when good men ſhall be rewarded accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their ſufferings, and wicked men puniſhed according to their deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings.</p>
            <p>If we do but hear two or three Malefactors receive their doom from the Judge, and ſee them led forth to Execution, we may thence conclude, that there ſhall be an univerſal doom; for it is not to be thought (ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) that ſeeing we have all one God, who is an upright Judge, that he would puniſh ſome men for their ſins in this world, and let others eſcape, which have offended as much or more than they, unleſs he had reſerved certain puniſhment for them alſo in the future World, at the day of judgement: and this is that which the Apoſtle hinteth to us, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. Some mens ſins are open before hand, and go before unto judgement, but ſome mens follow after. The ſins of ſome are known and manifeſt to the world, they are brought to Judgement, and they ſuffer for them here, their bodies are puniſhed, that their ſouls may be ſaved: but the ſins of ſome are cloſe, ſecret, unknown to the world, yet there will come a time, when they ſhall be revealed, when they ſhall be puniſhed; their ſins are upon the ſcore, and kept in ſtore, till the great day of reckoning; though they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the judgement of this world, yet they ſhall not eſcape the judgement of the world to come; their ſins ſhall follow after them, they ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them to judgement.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93067:7"/>
            <p> Now as it is moſt certain ſuch a day ſhall come, ſo moſt uncertain when it ſhall come. Some have raſhly and preſumptuouſly undertaken to gueſs at the time, and define when it ſhall be, as though they had been in the boſome of God, and were the Secretaries of Heaven. To whom it may be ſaid, as the <hi>Cynick</hi> to an ignorant and arrogant fellow, prating of Heavenly matters beyond his capacity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pray ſir, how lately came you from Heaven, that you know theſe things ſo well, or as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> telleth of one who anſwered that buſie Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who would know what God did before he made the world; <hi>fecit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernum, curioſa ſcrutantibus,</hi> he made Hell to puniſh thoſe who are too curious in prying into his ſecrets. Our Saviour tells us that when that day ſhall be, no man knoweth, no not the Angels of Heaven, which have farre more excellent knowledge than we; no, not he himſelf; that is, as man, he was ignorant of it, or had no commiſſion then to reveal it; or, as <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Dicitur neſcire, quia non facit ſcire;</hi> he is ſaid not to know, becauſe he will not make us to know. Therefore let no man preſume above his reach; ſecret things belong to the Lord, revealed things to us, and to our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; onely this we are ſure of, the time cannot be farre off, it is even at hand; It was near in the Apoſtles time, much more in our time; all the ſigns preceding fore-told by our Lord, and his holy Apoſtles, being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, except the calling of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which how ſoon, when, and in what manner it ſhall be, we know not. <hi>Behold the Judge ſtandeth even at the door; Yet a very little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry, Heb.</hi> 10. The world is now in <hi>decrepito ſtatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ,</hi> in a declining con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, drawing the laſt breath, at the laſt caſt, at the laſt gaſpe. As man who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a little world, ſo the world which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great man, (as the Philoſopher ſpeaks) hath its infancy, childe-hood, youth, middle age, old age: The time (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> was the worlds infancy; from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> its childe-hood; from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> its youth; from <hi>David</hi> to the Captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> its middle age; from the Captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> unto Chriſt, its old age; from Chriſt unto the end of all things, its dotage; for ever ſince, the world hath as it were gone upon Crutches, and therefore, now cannot ſtand long: if St. <hi>Johns</hi> age were <hi>ultima hora,</hi> the laſt hour, ſurely our times are the laſt minute of the hour. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the time is ſhort, the ſails are wrapp'd up, the Ship is even at hand, let us therefore uſe this world, as if we uſed it not. Let this ſhortneſs and ſpeedineſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten us to a ſpeedy preparation; the uncertainty of this day, to a daily and continual preparation; for that which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid of the day of death, may as well be ſaid of the day of Judgement; why did God hide from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93067:8"/>us the day of our death? was it not that every day we ſhould be prepared? <hi>ideolatet ultimus dies, &amp; obſerver un c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mis dies;</hi> The laſt day is concealed, that every day may be obſerved. So if any demand, why hath God hid from us this day of Judgement, why doth no man know when it ſhall be? I anſwer, It is becauſe we ſhould alwaies watch and wait for it; and as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſpeaks, ſo lead the courſe of our lives every day, as if to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhould be Dooms-day. This Application let us make of it; alwaies to Prepare: Becauſe then God will deal with every man according as hee findes him; he that is found ſmiting his fellow Servants, eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the drunken, ſhall be cut in pieces, and have his portion with the Hypocrites; but he that is found doing the command of our great Maſter, ſhall enter into eternal joy; for then God will deal to every man his right, and reward him according to his deſervings: And ſo I come to the laſt querie, or part of my Text, <hi>Quomodo,</hi> How he ſhall Judge? and that is <hi>ſecundum norman juſtitiae,</hi> according to the rule of juſtice, according to equity, according to right; <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Earth, do right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Righteous is the Lord in all his judgements; with righteouſneſs ſhall he judge the world, and the peole with equity.</hi> Pſal. 98.10. Some Examples of his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, he gives in this preſent world, as fore-runners of his upright dealing in the future world: rewarding the wicked according to the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their ſins, paying them juſt as they have deſerved, meaſuring to them the ſame meaſure they have meaſured, and puniſhing them in the ſame kinde, wherein they offended. It is ſaid, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 11.15, 16. That for their fooliſh devices, in worſhipping Serpents void of reaſon, and vile Beaſts; God ſent a multitude of unreaſonable beaſts upon them for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: that they might know, that wherewithal a man ſinneth, by the ſame alſo ſhall he be puniſhed, So <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt ſpoiled many Nations, all the remnant of the people ſhall ſpoil thee,</hi> and Jer. 30.16. <hi>All they that devour thee ſhall be devoured; and they that ſpoil thee ſhall be a ſpoil; and all that prey upon thee, will I give for a prey;</hi> And for proof of this, I might bring a cloud of witneſſes, and Examples: <hi>Sodomiticae illae civitates, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Thoſe <hi>Sodomitical</hi> Cities, that burned with filthy luſts, were juſtly burned with fire from above; and as they made a Hell upon earth by their beaſtlineſs and uncleanneſs, ſo <hi>Gehennam miſit è Coele,</hi> (as <hi>Silvianus</hi> ſpeaks) he ſent a Hell out of Heaven to conſume them for it. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that cauſed the ſilly Infants to be drowned in the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> was himſelf and all his Hoſt drowned in the Red Sea. <hi>Adonibezeck</hi> that cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeventy Kings, having the Thumbs of their right hands, and great Toes cut off, to gather crumbs under his Table, was ſerved with the ſame ſawce by <hi>Judah; As I have done, ſo hath God rewarded me,</hi> Judges 1.7. <hi>Judah</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93067:8"/>did it, yet he confeſſeth Gods Juſtice in it. The Dogs ear the fleſh of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> becauſe ſhe made them lick the blood of <hi>Nuboth. Haman</hi> hangs on his own Gallows, which he prepared for <hi>Mordecai.</hi> As <hi>Agags</hi> ſword had made many women childeleſs, ſo was his Mother by the ſword made childleſs among women. <hi>Maxentius</hi> falls into the ſame trap which he laid for <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his Lord and Maſter. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, by the miſtake of his Butler, was poiſoned with the ſame Bottle, wherewith he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to diſpatch his Cardinals. That brand of Hell, Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> Agent, was ſlain with the ſame inſtrument, wherewith he was hired to ſlay <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour: This Emperour being at <hi>Rome,</hi> uſed every morning to pray in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Maries,</hi> on Mount <hi>Aventine. Hildebrand</hi> ſuborned a wicked villain ſecretly to convey up to the rafters of the Church great and maſſie ſtones, and ſo to diſpoſe them, that as the Emperour was kneeling at his devotions, they might fall down upon his head, and daſh but his brains: but as this wretch, the miniſter of Popiſh cruelty, was haſtening his deſign, and ſitting a maſſie ſtone for the execution of his Treaſon, the ſtone fell down, and beat him down withall, which falling on the pavement by the juſt Judgment of God, daſhed in pieces the carkaſs of that traiterous workman.</p>
            <p>How miraculouſly doth he reveal murthers, revenging blood with blood? how frequently doth he give them their fill of blood, who delight in blood? As 'tis written of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who had been the occaſion of much blood-ſhed, that being taken by <hi>Tomyres</hi> Queen of <hi>Scythia,</hi> ſhe ſtruck off his head, and put it into a hogs-head of mans blood, with this exprobration of his cruelty, <hi>ſatiate ſunguine quem fuiſti &amp; cujus inſatiabilis fuiſti.</hi> Glut thy ſelf, and take thy fill of blood which thou haſt alwaies thirſted after, and of which thou haſt been unſatiable. The like almoſt we read of <hi>Joab,</hi> a man of blood who ſhed the blood of war in peace, and put the blood of war upon his girdle at was about his joyns, and in the ſhoos that were on his feet; baſely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> treacherouſly killing <hi>Honer</hi> the Son of <hi>Ner,</hi> and <hi>Amaſa</hi> the Son of <hi>Jether:</hi> and though by his power and greatneſs he long eſcaped vengeance, yet his hoar-head was not ſuffered to go down to the grave without blood, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.5, 6. How juſtly doth he ſcourge Whoremongers and Adulterers with the not and canker, even in thoſe parts wherein they offend? do we not ever and anon hear of ſome notorious drunkards drowned in ditches and puddles; or taken away by ſome ſudden diſaſter in the midſt of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, when they have neither wit, not will to repent, nor to cry ſo much as Lord have mercy upon us? I have read of a Thief ſtrangled, and ſo exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the ſheep that he ſtole; tying it by the legges, and carrying it on his head, and ſitting down to reſt upon a great ſtone by the way, the ſheep
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93067:9"/>ſtrugling, pulled him over the ſtone, and choaked him; ſo that he was found dead in the morning, and the ſheep alive (at <hi>Ailton</hi> in <hi>Huntington<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> Dr. <hi>Beard,</hi> Judg. pag. 570.)</p>
            <p>So he doth puniſh thoſe with diſobedient children, who have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to their Parents. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> writeth of one that did beat his own Father, and being reproved as guilty of ſo vile a fact, he anſwered, when he was as I am, he did beat his Father; and I make no doubt, but there ſtands one (pointing to his Son, then a childe) who will hereafter do the like to mee. Therefore by the nature of our puniſhment, we may know the nature of our ſin; for commonly the ſame meaſure is returned, that we have meaſured. Do we finde men ungrateful to us? let us ſearch, have not we been ungrateful to our God? if ſo, no marvel if men be ſo to us. By this means <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> came to ſee his ſin; I have (ſaid he) advanced many to honour and preferments, and heaped great favours upon them, and yet I ſtill finde them to be ungrateful: but ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine own heart, I do not much wonder at it, for I finde that I my ſelf being advanced by God, and having received great bleſſings; from him, have been unthankful to his heavenly Majeſty: and it is but juſt that men ſhould make ſuch a return to me, as I have made to my God. Are we puniſhed with the loſs of our worldly goods and ſubſtance? Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ſet our hearts too much upon them? or with ſickneſs? did not health make us wanton, and forgetful of our frail condition? Let, us thus, by the kind of puniſhment, ſearch out our ſin, that repenting, we may obtain pardon.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed, that God doth ſometimes uſe martial Law againſt the wicked, by remarkable ſtroaks of his Juſtice upon them, in this world; becauſe otherwiſe men would think there were no God, or at leaſt, that, he were not Juſt: but theſe, examples are but now and then; if he ſhould pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all in this world, men would think there were no Judgement to come, but that all were diſpatched here, and after this life, no more ado; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he defers the main execution of his Juſtice, till the end of the world, and then he will do right to every man: he will (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>render to every man according to his works,</hi> Rom. 2.6. both <hi>ſecundum qualitatem, &amp; ſecundum quantitatem,</hi> according to the quality, and according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He will judge us according to the quality of our works; he will render good for good, and evil for evil; not evil for good, not good for evil: <hi>To them who by patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and immortality, he will give eternal life. But unto them that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, and do not obey the Truth, but obey unrighteouſneſs, indignation and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93067:9"/>wrath, tribulation and anguiſh, upon every ſoul of man that doth evil, of the Jew firſt, and alſo of the Greek,</hi> Rom. 2.7, 8, 9. The good Tree that bringeth forth good fruit, ſhall be cheriſhed and preſerved: The evil Tree that bringeth forth evil fruit, ſhall be cut down and burned.</p>
            <p>O the vanity and folly of many worldlings, who go on in all ſin and wickedneſs, and yet hope to have a reward in Heaven, as well as the beſt I but God is an upright Judge; as he will not requite good with evil, ſo he will not reward evil with good. <hi>Do men gather Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi> If a man ſow Tares, can he expect a crop of Wheat? or if he ſow Cockle, can he look for a harveſt of Barley? <hi>Be not deceived,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>God is not mocked, for whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap; he that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption; but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting,</hi> Gal. 6.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He will judge us according to the quantity of our works; they that have moſt ſins, ſhall be adjudged to moſt torments; they that have moſt good works, to moſt glory. The ſentence is paſt already on the Whore of <hi>Babylon, quantum in diliciis fuit,</hi> for ſo much pleaſure, give her ſo much pain: ſo much for ſo much; a moſt righteous Judge. The ignorant ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſhall be adjudged to few ſtripes, the negligent ſervant to many ſtripes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47, 48. <hi>Woe unto you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Widdows houſes, and for a pretence make long prayers; therefore ye ſhall receive the greater damnation,</hi> Mat. 23.14. So that ſome ſhall have greater damnation than others.</p>
            <p>See here the pittiful folly of ſome deſperate wretches, who being given over to a reprobate ſenſe, to commit all filthineſs with greedineſs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reproved and admoniſhed to run better courſes, and ſhewed the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their waies, how they will bring bitterneſs at laſt; ſollace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with this miſerable comfort; oh we know the worſt of it, we can be but damned! Alas, alas, they know not, conſider not what it is to be damned; an horrid, hideous, unexpreſſible, irrecoverable miſchief to be damned; and how there are degrees of damnation too: the more ſins, the more ſtripes; and how that thoſe who ſin againſt light, knowledge and conſcience, careleſs and wicked Chriſtians, ſhall be thruſt deeper into Hell, and ſcorched in hotter flames than Infidels and Pagans; for our Lord aſſures us in the Goſpel, That it ſhall be eaſier for <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sydon,</hi> than for <hi>Bethſaida</hi> and <hi>Corazin,</hi> at the day of doom: and that ſinful <hi>Sodom</hi> ſhall ſpeed better than proud <hi>Capernaum</hi> at the laſt day. Doubtleſs <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Sydon,</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſhall be damned, and have moſt dreadful puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Hell, in that lake which never ſhall be quenched, where the worm dieth not, and the fire never goeth out: But <hi>Bethſaida, Corazin,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93067:10"/>Capernaum,</hi> ſhall have more dreadful puniſhments, more fearful torments: why? becauſe <hi>Bethſaida, Corazin, Capernaum,</hi> had means of ſalvation, heard Chriſt, and ſaw Chriſt; heard his Doctrine, and ſaw his miracles, and yet repented not, believed not; whereas <hi>Tyrus, Sydon, Sodom,</hi> had no ſuch means; therefore their puniſhment ſhall be lighter, the others heavier.</p>
            <p>He will alſo reward our good works, according to their quantity, ſo much for ſo much, though he will not reward us, to ſpeak properly, <hi>prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opera,</hi> for our works, yet <hi>ſecundum opera,</hi> according to our works, as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith; though not for the meer merit of them, yet according to the meet meaſure of them: our good works ſhall be the rule by which he will proportion out the heavenly reward: the more good works of grace we have, the more abundant will be our reward of glory. <hi>Every man ſhall receive his own reward, according to his own labour,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.8. He that uſeth five Talents well, ſhall be Ruler over five Cities; he that uſeth ten Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents well, ſhall be Ruler over ten Cities, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.17.19. <hi>They that be wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament; but they that turn many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the ſtars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12.3. And as our Lord ſaith, <hi>tune fulgebunt Juſti tanquam Sol, Then ſhall the Juſt ſhine as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father,</hi> Mat. 13.43. In Heaven among the Saints, there ſhall be degrees of glory; as there is difference now among the ſtars of Heaven in beauty: <hi>One ſtar differeth from another ſtar in glory,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>There is one glory the Sun, another of the Moon, another of the Stars;</hi> ſo ſhall it be with the Saints in the Kingdom of Heaven; every Saint ſhall have glory enough, yet ſome more, ſome leſs, according to the proportion of their faith and good works. As all behold the Sun, yet not according to the ſame perfect brightneſs; but ſome more, ſome leſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of their ſight: ſo the Saints in Heaven ſhall all have the beatifical Viſion of God, yet ſome in more perfect manner than other, according to the meaſure of their graces here: Or, as if a man caſt divers Bottles into the Sea, of ſeveral capacities, ſome greater, ſome leſs; every one will be filled, yet the greateſt will receive moſt: So, though all the Saints ſhall be filled with glory, and every one have as much as he can contain, yet thoſe who do moſt abound in faith and good works, ſhall have moſt glory.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This may admoniſh us how careful we ought to be of our works; to be practical and working Chriſtians, <hi>to add to our faith good works;</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth Believers, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Giving all diligence, add to your faith vertue, &amp;c. godlineſs, brotherly kindneſs, charity.</hi> Though we allow not the merit of works, yet we teach the neceſſity of good works, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93067:10"/>fruits, and evidences of true faith; and becauſe the reward of glory ſhall be proportioned out according to our works; look what our works be, ſuch ſhall be the verdict that ſhall paſs upon us at the great day. Therefore, ſaith <hi>James, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works:</hi> Thou ſayeſt thou haſt faith, and talkeſt much of it, but let it appear by the fruits, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence a right faith by a righteous life. It is ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.20. That Chriſt ſaw their faith: and healed the man of the Palſie: he ſaw not only with the eye of his Divinity, but by their works, by the effects and fruits of it, he ſaw their faith: for they laid the ſick man on a bed, brought him after Chriſt, and when they could not come near him for the multitude, they opened the roof, and let him down in his Couch before him: when Chriſt ſaw their faith, by theſe not able works, he healed the ſick man. If thou wilt have Chriſt to heal thee, to ſave thee, thou muſt let him ſee thy faith by thy works. We read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.21.22. That old <hi>Iſaac</hi> would not bleſs <hi>Jacob</hi> by his ſpeech or voice only, but feels and handles him firſt; <hi>Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee my Son, whether thou be my very Son Eſau or not;</hi> and when he found they were <hi>Eſau</hi>'s hands, he bleſſed him. So Chriſt will not pronounce his bleſſing upon us by out voice or words on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> He will handle and ſeel us, and if he finde working hands, that we have been open-handed to his poor Saints, he will bleſs us, and give us the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his heavenly Kingdom. How ſhould the remembrance of this ſtir us up to the practice of good deeds, to be alwaies abounding in the work of the Lord? for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to our practice that Chriſt will reward us at the laſt day. So it is in the Evangeliſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 27. The word is for the moſt part taken in a good ſenſe, and noteth an acting after the precepts of good manners; as a learned Critick noteth, <hi>Keck.</hi> in <hi>Ethic.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to our works: So it is in <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 2.6. Therefore I will conclude with the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 18, 19. <hi>Do good, and be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, and that ye may lay hold on eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the conſideration of this alſo, turn our worldly ambition into an holy ambition; our earthly covetouſneſs, into heavenly covetouſneſs: we do contend and cover, who ſhall be chief here on earth; who ſhall ſit higheſt at our Feaſts, and have the chief place in the Synagogue; who ſhall out-ſtrip others in gay Apparel; and who ſhall have moſt wealth and riches, and who ſhall have the ſtatelieſt houſes. Oh then let us be as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, contentious and ambitious for heavenly glory, who ſhall have the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93067:11"/>higheſt ſeat, the chiefeſt place there, the faireſt Manſion there: for there be many Manſions; <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many Manſions;</hi> there be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per rooms, and there be lower rooms; there be higher ſeats, and there be lower ſeats, there is greater glory, and there is leſſer glory: Let us therefore ſtrive, who ſhall be moſt zealous of Gods glory here, ſo ſhall we be ſure to have the more glorious reward here after; For God is a moſt juſt Judge, he will give to every man his right, he will render to every man according to his works; <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the earth do right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me crave your honourable patience to add a few words for applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I have done: you have heard how we muſt all appear before this Almighty Judge, where wrong ſhall be righted, and right rewarded. Let this move us all in our ſeveral Callings and ſtations, to keep a good Conſcience, and take heed to the thing that is right, which will bring peace at laſt; for if any man do wrong, he ſhall receive for the wrong he hath done, and there is no reſpect of perſons with God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, reverend and honourable Sages, ye who now ſit on the Throne of Judgement to judge others: remember the day will quickly come, when ye muſt appear before a Judgement ſeat to be judged your ſelves: have that great Judge ſtill before your eyes, his fear in your hearts, (as I doubt not but ye alwaies have) and let all your Actions be ſuch, that ye may ſtand before him without fear, with joy and comfort at that day. Let not friends nor favour, paſſion nor affection cauſe you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to the right hand or to the left, remember the judgement is the Lords, in whoſe place ye ſit; whoſe vice-gerents ye are on earth, let his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be the ſquare of all your proceedings, your judgement like his, <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum norman Juſtitiae,</hi> according to the rule of Juſtice, equity and right; your charge is great, being well diſcharged, your reward's the greater: As St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, the Elders that Rule well, ſo the Judges that judge well, are worthy of double honour, they deſerve it in this world; they ſhall be ſure to have it in the future world; this impartial Judge will do right, and recompence them according to their works.</p>
            <p>In the next place, worſhipful and worthy Commiſſioners, ye which now ſit Aſſiſtants on the Bench, let your actions be ſuch, that ye may alſo ſit aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants with this Heavenly Judge at the laſt day, and be in the number of the Saints (which the Lord in mercy grant.) St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> laid it to the charge of the old <hi>Romans,</hi> that they were more tender of their own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, than of the honour of their Gods; if any one had wrong'd a Senator, but in a word, he was ſure to ſmoak for it; but they ſuffered their Poets to quip and whip their Gods, and never queſtioned them for it. I hope you are free from any ſuch imputation; of being more forward in revenging your own wrongs, than Gods wrongs. Yet give me leave, humbly to put
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93067:11"/>a caſe to you; If Drunkards, Blaſphemers, Swearers, Adulterers, Riotous, Debauched, Atheiſtical, prophane perſons, who forget the God that made them, and deny the Lord that bought them, who kick at his Word and worſhip, who ſcorne at holineſs, and ſcoffe away Religion, and jeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way holy Scripture, or directly cry it down, daring to Blaſpheme and ſay, it is the voice of man, and not of God, as in truth it is, I <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. whoſe madneſs is manifeſt enough to all, and deſerves a ſevere check. who ſwear away our mercies, and curſe away our bleſſings, and drink away their healths, by drinking healths; and do what in them lies to damne their precious ſouls, having <hi>God damne me,</hi> more often than <hi>Lord have mercy,</hi> in their mouthes; who ſhew their ſins like <hi>Sodom,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them with an Harlots face, without ſhame or bluſhing, by whom God is more diſhonoured, than by any other; ſhall ſwarme in your ſeveral Diviſions, perhaps in ſome of your Families, and yet be ſeldome or never queſtioned, cenſured, or puniſhed, at leaſt by ſome of you: Are ye not too ſlack in vindicating Gods honour? I appeal to your own hearts. Surely, a heavy clog will at laſt lye upon their Souls and Conſciences, by whoſe connivence ſin is nurtured and increaſed, when it is in their hand to reſtrain it. If ye will not do juſtice on them, the time is coming, when the great Lord-Chief-Juſtice of the world, will do juſtice both on you and them; on them for ſinning, and on you for ſuffering them. For <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the World do right?</hi> A ſad thing it is, (and ſorry I am, I muſt ſpeak this, to our ſhame) That a greater reſtraint ſhould be put upon ſin, and foul enormities, under the uſurped powers, than under the true, juſt and lawful powers: <hi>Will ye ſo requite the Lord, O fooliſh people, and unwiſe? Is not he thy Father, that hath bought or redeemed and eſtabliſhed thee?</hi> ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 22.6. And ſhall we thus requite the Lord for the ſignal mercies, the great things, the wonders he hath done for us in the bleſſed reſtauration of our King, our Religion, Laws and liberties? God forbid. For this the mouth of the Adverſary is open againſt us; (though they ſee not their own ſins of ſtubbornneſs, diſobedience, murmuring, Schiſm, Hereſie, as vile in Gods ſight, though not ſo viſible to the world.) Yea, I fear, the Lord hath a Controverſie with our Land for this, for this his fierce anger is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill, <hi>For this gird thee with ſackcloath, O</hi> England, <hi>weep and howl; and let thine eyes run down with tears, night and day, and let them not ceaſe.</hi> This is a lamentation, and ſhall be for a lamentation, till it be reformed.</p>
            <p>But do ye deſire to redreſs theſe abuſes (as I hope you do?) then let me humbly commend to you, two or three directions. 1. Put in Execution the good laws more duely. 2. give good example your ſelves more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93067:12"/>ſincerely. 3. Leſſen the occaſions thereof more effectually; by taking away clandeſtine, blinde, and ſuperfluous Ale-houſes, the Peſt-houſes of the Nation. Let them not be like the head of <hi>Hydra,</hi> when one is cut off, two to ſtart up in the place thereof. I have read of a certain ſtreet in <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Vicus Sobrius,</hi> the ſober ſtreet, perhaps becauſe there was never a tippling-houſe in it; which is hard to be ſaid of any ſtreet in <hi>England;</hi> but ſurely both our Towns, Streets, and Villages, would be more ſober, if the number of theſe needleſs houſes were diminiſhed. The King of <hi>Meth,</hi> ſometime in <hi>Ireland,</hi> asked one how certain noiſome birds, that came flying into his Realm, and bred there, might be deſtroyed; who anſwered, <hi>nidos eorum ubique deſtruendos;</hi> that the only way to rid them out of the Land, was to deſtroy and pull down their neſts. Do you deſire to leſſen the number of thoſe noiſome birds, and unclean beaſts, that defile our Land? your beſt way is to pull down the neſts, where they are brood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the dens, where they are harboured; blind and baſe Ale-houſes, which are the neſts and Nurſeries of all vices: There quarrels are bred, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers occaſioned, oaths coyned, robberies plotted, thieves harboured, whoredomes committed; and to conclude, they are the very dens and cages of all uncleanneſs.</p>
            <p>Let me add one Word to <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> the learned of the Law, and all who relate to it; remember, the hour is coming, wherein they who plead for others, ſhall not plead for themſelves; where unleſs they now work the Judge to be their friend, by keeping faith and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they ſhall have none to plead for them. I ſay not to you, as our Saviour to thoſe in his time, <hi>Woe be to you Lawyers, I hope better things of you and ſuch as accompany ſalvation.</hi> Only give me leave to make a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, if there bee any which blow up the coals of diſſention among neighbours, to warm their own fingers at the fire; who tell their Client, his Cauſe is good, when in their conſcience they know it to be ſtark naught; who ſay good is evil, and evil good; who put light for darkneſs, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for light; ſweet for bitter, and bitter for ſweet; who make truth falſhood, and falſhood truth; whoſe tongues cannot move nimbly, and ſo by ſilence ſmother the poor mans right, becauſe he hath but one Angel to move the waters; any <hi>Ambidexters,</hi> that can take fees on both ſides; or for a larger fee, prove turn-coats, and go to the other ſide; <hi>vae illis,</hi> woe be to them! the time is at hand, when they will finde it no profit to gain a world, and loſe a ſoul. There is one on high, that looks into their hearts, and ſees their ſhuffling and jugling, their deceit and fraud, though never ſo ſecret from the world, and will diſcover all to their ſhame and confuſion. I have heard of a certain kinde of writing, ſo cunningly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93067:12"/>framed in Paper, without any appearance, that it cannot poſſibly be read unleſs one hold it againſt the fire; then the letters and characters appear plain to the ſight. Imagine this Paper to be a mans heart, the letters written therein, his thoughts, intents and purpoſes; which perhaps none can now diſcover, for no man knoweth the things of a man, but the ſpirit of a man that is in him: yet when we come to the fire at dooms day, all ſhall be laid open; when the heart and conſcience ſhall be laid to the fire of the laſt Judgement, which ſhall try every mans work; the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thoughts and aims thereof ſhall be made manifeſt; then God <hi>will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and make manifeſt the counſels of the heart,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 5. Yea, <hi>then he will judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 2. 16. <hi>For there is nothing covered, that ſhall not be revealed, neither hid that ſhall not be known.</hi> Luk. 12. 2.</p>
            <p>In the next place, Jury-men, ſtand forth and hear your charge; all good men and true, ſee ye be, look to your oaths, ſee you break them not; let not favour or affection, ſpleen or paſſion, draw you aſide: perjury, a ſin moſt dangerous, almoſt unpardonable, becauſe the perjured perſon doth mortgage his ſoul to eternal damnation; deſiring God ſo to help him, as he ſweareth truly; ſo that if he fail in his oath, by not performing, if promiſſory; by not ſpeaking the truth, and whole truth, if aſſertory, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires no favour, no mercy at Gods hands; and then what a fearful caſe is he in? no favour he deſires; and God will give him according to his deſires, and to his deſerts; let him be ſure of it; for will not the Judge of all the earth do right?</p>
            <p>Therefore in the laſt place, witneſſes, and you that come to give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in any matter, be well adviſed, look before ye leap: if by a falſe oath, or falſe evidence, the innocent be oppreſſed, and Juſtice perverted, will not the Judge of all the world revenge it? yes ſurely, he is a juſt Judge againſt falſe witneſſes, and falſe ſwearers; and threatens himſelf againſt falſe ſwearers, to be a ſwift witneſs, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt.</hi> relateth a memorable example in this kind, upon three ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Varlets, who falſly accuſed <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of a hainous crime, confirming it with deſperate imprecations? the firſt wiſhed, if it were not true, that he might be burnt to aſhes; the ſecond, that he might dye of the Jaundies; the third, that he might loſe both his eyes. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> not being able to reſiſt them, fled and hid himſelf: but ſhortly after God gave them their right; the firſt, by the fall of one ſpark of fire in the night, had himſelf and all his family conſumed to aſhes: the ſecond was ſurrounded and tormented in his whole body, with the diſeaſe he wiſhed, and dyed miſerably; the third ſeeing their ends, and fearing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93067:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>vengeance, confeſſed the miſchief, and mourned and wept for it, till at length he loſt both his eyes: or if ye ſhould eſcape in this world, will not vengeance attend you in the other? if ye ſin againſt knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is it not a double ſin? and will it not be repaid with a double torment? yes, be ſure it will; for the Judge of all the earth will do right.</p>
            <p>I will ſhut up all with the Epilogue of <hi>Solomon,</hi> to his Book called <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> the two laſt <hi>verſes. Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter; fear God, and keep bis Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man; for God ſhall bring every work into Judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
